<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assises held at York, July the 23d. 1683. Not long after the discovery of the late horrid conspiracy against his Majesties person and government. / By Henry Constantine, M.A.</title>
            <author>Constantine, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C947A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174230</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52211995</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52211995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175604</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02593)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175604)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2742:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assises held at York, July the 23d. 1683. Not long after the discovery of the late horrid conspiracy against his Majesties person and government. / By Henry Constantine, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Constantine, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 33, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Grantham, for Isaac Cleave at the Star, next to Serjeants-Inn in Chancery-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>[2] p. at end: Books printed and sold by Isaac Cleave.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXV, 5 --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Rye House Plot, 1683 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Assize sermons --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175604:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175604:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preached at the ASSISES HELD AT YORK, <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LY</hi> the 23<hi>d.</hi> 1683. Not long after the Diſcovery of the late Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Conſpiracy againſt His Majeſties Perſon and Government.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY CONSTANTINE,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROVERBS XXV. 5.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take away the wicked from before the King, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Grantham,</hi> for <hi>Iſaac Cleave</hi> at the <hi>Star,</hi> next to <hi>Serjeants-Inn</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:175604:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:175604:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Worſhipful</hi> AMBROSE P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DSAY <hi>Eſq; High-Sheriff of the County of</hi> YORK.</head>
            <p>AS this ſhort Sermon ows its Birth unto you, ſo it ſeeks its Patronage from you; you commanded it to the Pulpit, and adviſed it to the Preſs; ſo that both the nature of the Subject, and your intereſt in the Preacher have made it wholly yours; and though its haſty Birth denyed it that juſt proportion, and thoſe Lineaments which a longer time would have given, yet I hope the Honeſty of the deſign will attone for the defects of the Diſcourſe: I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded little to what I then ſpoke, and have omitted nothing but a forward Parentheſis which had given ſome diſguſt: None can juſtly Quarrel with the Character which is laid down, but ſuch as are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to themſelves how much they deſerve it; and no great wonder if theſe (having over-lived their Duty and Allegiance) like aged <hi>Lais</hi> ſtrive to break the Glaſs which ſhows them their own Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; but I ſhall more eaſily bear the ſevereſt of their Cenſures, when I have gained your approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:175604:3"/> whoſe Eminent Zeal, and Faithfulneſs to His Majeſties Service, renders you fit for that great truſt which he has now repoſed in you; and ſhows how much you inherit the Vertue, and untainted Loyalty of your Antient Family, the proſperity and continuance whereof, is deſired, and hoped for by all that have the Honour and Happineſs of being known unto you; but by no man with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Zeal, than by him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>The moſt Humble, and moſt Faithful of your Servants. <hi>HENRY CONSTANTINE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175604:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the Aſſiſes held at <hi>YORK, July</hi> the 23<hi>d.</hi> 1683. Not long after the Diſcovery of the late Horrid Conſpiracy againſt His Majeſties Perſon and Government,</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROV. XXV. 5.</bibl>
               <q>Take away the wicked from before the King, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HEaven alone is that happy place where we can promiſe to our ſelves the enjoyment of an undiſturbed Peace, nor can any other Throne than the Throne of God receive ſo firm an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, as to ſecure it from the bold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of malicious and Blood-thirſty men, and from thoſe miſerable revolutions which have buried many flouriſhing Kingdoms in the ſaddeſt heaps of their own Ruins: Thunders happen only in the lower Regions of the Air,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175604:4"/> whilſt the Orbs above are calm and clear; thus we who are left to people this lower Vale of Tears, lye more open to the ſtrokes of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Sedition, whilſt the Bleſſed Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Manſions above are ſet out of the reach of thoſe Blows, and are ſecured from the very fears of ſuch a fatal change. Once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, <hi>Lucifer</hi> the Grand-ſire of all this Modern brood of Rebels durſt deſign a Change even in Heaven it ſelf; but being thrown Head-long down from thence, he riſes full of rage, and finding himſelf too ſhort handed to reach the Throne of God, he turns his revenge againſt the Thrones of Princes; he ſtrives to wound the Almighty in Effigie, in the moſt noble part of his Image, and to ſtrike him through the Sides of thoſe that are his Vicegerents and Repreſentatives here on Earth: To this end he Muſters up all his Legionary Forces, he Trains them in his cloſe Cabals, where they ſit brood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over that Spawn of Treaſon which he has infus'd, till they be ready to March upon ſome fatal Service. He taught <hi>Cain</hi> in the worlds Infancy, not to take it well, that his Brother <hi>Abel</hi> ſhould be the greater Favourite in the Court of Heaven; and when he lodg'd ſo much
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175604:4"/> Envy in his Heart, he found it more eaſy to put the Weapon into his hand; inſomuch, that he who thought it an unreaſonable thing, at Gods Demand, to be his Brothers Keeper, was drawn at the Devils inſtigation to be his Murtherer. It had fared better with all after Ages, if the crimes of Envy and Ambition had been buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Brothers Graves, beyond the poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Reſurrection; but alaſs, they grew rather to a greater height with the growing world: the corrupted nature of Man become<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but too fruitful a Seed-plot of thoſe vices, which in time gathered ſo much ſtrength, that they turn'd Uſurpers, ſnatch'd the Scepters out of the hands of many Princes, hurl'd the World into confuſion, filling every Kingdom with Sedition, and every corner with Blood: No Body Politick can be found, which has not ſometimes groan'd and bled under the blows which theſe Crimes have given; and if it have ſurviv'd a civil death, yet has it long after felt the ſmart, and ſeen the Scars of its former wounds: Nor is there any Crown upon Earth which has not received a deeper Tincture of Red from the Blood of thoſe that contended for it, than its own Gold could ever give. But
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175604:5"/> where any Kingdom, for the Excellency of its Conſtitution, for the Purity of its Religion, and for the Prudence of its Governour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a nearer Type of Heaven, and condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more to the happineſs of Men, there it lies more expos'd to the rage and malice of Hell; and there all the Devils Engines are at work for its deſtruction. No wonder then, if ſo many Pioneers of his have been employed to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the foundation of our eſtabliſhed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which juſtly deſerves the higheſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. <hi>Africa</hi> ſhall no longer boaſt of her ſtrange productions, ſince our own Land is every age, nay, every luſtre almoſt, teeming with ſuch Black Monſters of Ingratitude and Rebellion, as are a ſhame to our Kingdom; a ſcandal to Religion: and a reproach unto Manknd. It has been put in the Catalogue of our Engliſh Bleſſings, that (by the care of our Princes) we are now free from Wolves, and other Beaſts of Prey, which in the former times were ſo numerous and burthenſome; but now, as if their Savageneſs and Cruelty, had by a ſtrange kind of μετεμψύχωσις, paſt into ſome of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants themſelves, we may complain of it as the Miſery and Grievance of our Nation, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175604:5"/> we are over-ſtock'd with a company of dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Creatures, who lye covered in their Clubs and Conventicles, (thoſe Dens of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) and are more inconſiſtant with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace and ſafety, than thoſe wild Beaſts ever were; <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 15. Cunning Foxes, ſuch as would break down the Strongeſt Fence, and ſpoil the choiceſt Fruits of our Vineyard; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Wolves, ſuch as would not only tear in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſome of the meaner Flock, and glut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Slaughter of the common Herd; but would ſtrike the Shepherd, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (for ſo the Prince is called) and would quench their unnatural and ambitious thirſt in ſtreams of Royal Blood. Nor is it eaſy to determine, whether the villany of ſo curſed a deſign, or the mercy of our deliverance be the greater miracle; we may juſtly raiſe a Pillar for the monument of our thankfulneſs, and may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave it with <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Motto, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 12. <hi>Hitherto the Lord hath helped us.</hi> We have long ſailed in the Straits, between the <hi>Popiſh Scylla</hi> an the <hi>Fanatical Charibdis;</hi> and whilſt ſome feared that our care to avoid the one would inſenſibly caſt us upon the other, we have not hitherto ſplit upon either of thoſe Rocks
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175604:6"/> which threaten our Ruine; the Sun is ſtill in our Firmament, the light of our Eyes is not darkned; nor is the breath of our Noſtrils ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired: nor is the Crown fallen from our Heads. Which wonderful deliverance we owe chiefly to the watchful care of Almighty God, who, when the wretches went big with Treaſon, made the burthen prove abortive, and cruſhed thoſe <hi>Cockatrices</hi> Eggs e're they had time to turn Serpents, or to exert their Stings. We owe it alſo to the Wiſdom of our dear and dread Soveraign, the tutelar Angel of the Kingdoms peace; to the faithfulneſs of his Councellors, and to the dilligence of his Miniſters; nor ſhould any one of us at ſuch a critical time as this, in our reſpective places, be wanting to the defence of his Sacred Perſon, and the ſecurity of his Government: we ſhould ſet banks to that deluge which threatens us with an innundation of Blood. Miniſters ſhould Preach Loyalty, People ſhould practice Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and they to whom the Sword of Juſtice is committed, ſhould <hi>Take away the Wicked from before the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Throne was nearer Heaven, than the Thrones of his Neighbouring Princes; he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175604:6"/> had a clearer eye to find out thoſe who are the bane of Government, and a more impartial hand to puniſh them; and upon this account was left by <hi>David</hi>'s laſt Will and Teſtament, the Executor of that Vengeance which was to be inflicted on the remnant of thoſe Rebels, who were concern'd in <hi>Abſolom's,</hi> and in <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophels</hi> Conſpiracy; and having by ſuch an execution, ſecured the Peace of his own, he preſcribes it as the moſt effectual means for the eſtabliſhment of all other Kingdoms; and lays it down as the great Maxime of Pollicy and Government in the words of my Text, where he proceeds, <hi>a Remotione Mali,</hi> from the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of thoſe evils that are ſo inconſiſtant with the Kings ſafety, and the Kingdoms peace; <hi>Ad poſitionem boni,</hi> to the determining of that Bleſſing wherein the great happineſs of a Society does conſiſt, which is the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Kings Throne in Righteouſneſs;</hi> the preſerving and delivering down of Monarchy in its <hi>Right-Line</hi> to ſucceeding Ages, that they alſo may ſit ſafely, rejoicing under the ſhadow of that beſt of Governments which now is, and may it ever be, our Glory and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: a fit Pattern for the Repairers of our breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175604:7"/> who ſhould firſt remove the Rubbiſh, ſhould firſt take away the bane and burthen of Government, and then may better lay the Foundation, and raiſe the Fabrick of our Kingdoms Peace.</p>
            <p>I ſhall obſerve the ſame Method, and ſhall begin, <hi>a remotione mali,</hi> with the removal of that which is ſo abſolutely inconſiſtent with the juſt Eſtabliſhment of the Regal Throne. <hi>Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Wicked from before the King.</hi> Where we may find theſe three things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. An act of Juſtice, <hi>Take away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſubjects of this act, or the Character of thoſe perſons who are to be taken away, they are the <hi>Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Reaſon of this removal; becauſe the ſuffering of ſuch is not conſiſtent with the ſafety of his perſon, nor with the due ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of his Throne, therefore muſt they be taken away from before the King; And of theſe three parts in their order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Then, we have an act of Juſtice, <hi>Take away.</hi> Had but Mankind retained their primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive innocence, there would have been no need of ſuch a ſeparation; the Earth would have been filled with Righteouſneſs, and the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175604:7"/> whole World with Truth; then would Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Treaſon, War, and Murther have been ſuch ſtrangers, that even their hateful names would never have been ſo much as heard in our Streets; then would there have been ſuch an univerſal conformity of all things and perſons, to the great deſign and end of their Creation, that no crime, nor errour would have been committed; therefore no puniſhment could have been deſerved. The wickedneſs of men firſt cauſed the Sword of Juſtice to be drawn, and has ſound employment for it ever ſince; Sin breeds, and feeds thoſe bad humours in the Bowels of a Nation, which muſt either be removed, or they will quickly tend to its diſſolution: This gives many wounds to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy pollitick, and cauſes it to break out into thoſe Wens and Excreſencies of Government, which muſt be taken away, leaſt they ſhould grow more ſpreading and infectious. Sufference is but a bad Chyrurgion, which inſtead of heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing does but widen our Wounds and Breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. The greateſt offenders grow more bold and impudent, when they are buoy'd up with the hopes of a forbearance; and make the moſt deſperate attempts, when they can work under
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175604:8"/> the protection of an indulgence. Lay but the Reins in the Neck of ſome Head-ſtrong Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and they'l immediatly throw their Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, will tread down the Laws of Heaven, and Earth, and will violate all civil and ſacred Rights. Let ſuch tares grow ſtill amongſt us, and our Land will in a little time be like the Slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards Field, the Weeds would ſuck all the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſweetneſs to themſelves; would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-top and bear down all before them: would make our Kingdom a Map of Miſery, and would quickly turn it into an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a Field of Blood. Execution is the very life of the Law, without which it will prove but an inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Scare-crow, not able to keep the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſort of Mortals within the compaſs of their duty; like that dead log which every Frog in the Marſh could deſpiſe, and leap on at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. The diſcovery of an evil, without the power to remove it, is but an addition to our miſery, and makes the blow more deep and dreadful. Nature, therefore for our own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, has given us as many hands to take away what's hurtful to us, as it has given eyes to find it out; nor will the greateſt offender ever fear the eyes of the Jurors in their enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175604:8"/> after his crimes, if he never feels the hands of the Judge in the execution of thoſe Laws that are made for his puniſhment. Pity to ſome ſort of perſons, is cruelty to the reſt of the Kingdom; and whilſt we become their advocates, we become our own Traytors, and lay open our naked Breaſts to the ſtroke of thoſe Weapons, which our forbearance has unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily put into their hands: ſo that by this means we may make that ſad Exchange which <hi>Ahab</hi> was threatned with, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20. 42. our Life may go for their Life, and our people for their people. Thus to ſuffer the known Enemies of our Church and State tamely to compleat their intended villanies, were but to liſt our ſelves in the number of thoſe Rebels, and to become guilty of a notorious Miſpriſion of Treaſon. 'Tis a received Maxime: <hi>Qui non prohibet pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care quum poſſit jubet,</hi> He that does not ſtand up in his place, to take away theſe troublers of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when it it is in his power to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and prevent their intended Treaſon, does but joyn forces with them, and becomes one of that infamous number.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhould the multitudes of thoſe who are concerned in ſuch a Crime make it more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175604:9"/>
'Tis true, theſe render the Execution of Juſtice an act of greater difficulty; but they make it an act of greater neceſſity; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all Loyal perſons with an oppertunity of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving greater Teſtimonies of their Courage, and Fidelity to the World: Nor ſhould their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer favours be any bar to their preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval, Juſtice knows no Relations; and though the diſpencers of it, may, upon any civil account, accompany their Friends, μ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>χ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Βωμοῦ, even unto the Altars, yet in criminal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they can attend them no further than μ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>χ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Β<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ματος, to the judgment Seat, where (like that God whom they repreſent) they muſt weigh the merits of the cauſe without any reſpect unto the perſons, and muſt overlook the ſometimes unſeaſonable conſiderations of Nature, and affection, which ſome of the greateſt examples of Juſtice have ſo little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they have been ready to ſacrifice what was deareſt to them, when ſuch a victim was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to the publick peace and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Nor has their eye ſpared the moſt intimate of their Friends and Favourites; and indeed the Ear and the Tongue are only in the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> for the Tryal of ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175604:9"/> cauſes; the one to hear the Evidence, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pronounce the Sentence; the Eye is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. Hence it is that Juſtice is painted blind; and for this reaſon the <hi>Athenian</hi> Judges are ſaid to have kept their great Courts of Judicature in the night only, that the ſight of the perſon might not influence them in the determination of the cauſe; and that an inconvenient pity might not encline them to ſpare, and ſuffer thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffenders, whom the ſtronger motives of their own Duty, and the common ſafety, did engage them to remove, and take away; but even in the broad day, Treaſon in a Favourite looks more black and hateful to the World, than it does in one of the meaner croud, who is decoy'd only into the Conſpiracy; nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it appears in ſuch diſmal and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding colours to the Traytor himſelf, that after a ſerious reflexion upon his own ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and infidelity, ſuch pangs of deſpair and guilt do ſeize upon him, that not waiting for the formalities of the Law, he ſnatches the Sword into his own hand, and becomes his own Executioner.</p>
            <p>Say not, that it ill becomes an Embaſſador of the God of Peace to blow the Trumpet of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175604:10"/> War, and ſound an Alarm to a freſh perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (for under that invidious name, ſome are reſolved to expoſe the execution of our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws) when its nothing more than a juſt proſecution of ſuch delinquents, whoſe crimes are inconſiſtant with the publick peace that I am pleading for: And this the prodigious wickedneſs of ſome men renders too ſadly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and neceſſary. One would think, that thoſe who are conſcious of their own guilt, ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, condemned in themſelves, and calmly ſubmit to their deſerved puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but if they be truly Innocent, they need never fear the penalty of our ſevereſt Laws; nor did I ever hear the boldeſt enemies of our Government, dare to arraign the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Juſtice of our Nation, where the greateſt Criminals are allow'd the priviledge of their own witneſs, and defence: nor is any Sentence given, but upon a full Hearing, and clear Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in the judgment of Twelve unconcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and impartial perſons at the leaſt, againſt whom the Priſoner has the liberty of making his own Exceptions, and that ſometimes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving the reaſons of ſuch a refuſal. God forbid that we ſhould make the Righteous as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175604:10"/> the wicked; or that we ſhould ſo far imitate the cruelties of ſome former times, as to clothe the Innocent in the Skins of Wolves and Bears, to repreſent them to the World as the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Monſters of Fanaticiſme and Sedition, and then ſhould bring them forth to be torn in pieces by the ſanguinary Teeth of our penal Laws. No, <hi>Ex ungue leonem,</hi> the marks of their villanies do betray their guilt; and we charge none but ſuch men, whoſe ſeditious principles, and rebellious practices are ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that the Kings Throne can never firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be eſtabliſhed, unleſs they be removed and taken away.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This brings me to the ſecond part of my Text, to the Subjects of this act, or the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of thoſe perſons againſt whom the Sword of Juſtice is to be drawn. Should we take out of the Body of a Kingdom, what every zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous brain-ſick perſon judges inconſiſtent with its peace and ſafety; ſhould we change and reform things after the model of ſome mens extravagant fancies, and wild apprehenſions, we ſhould make it ſtrangely monſtrous, and miſhapen; what they preſcribe for our Cure would prove our Diſeaſe; and ſo many remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175604:11"/> would be made, that we ſhould have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle left but confuſion. Let but ſome giddy Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines have the guidance of this Sword; let them but reform and remove at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and they would quickly take away our Beauties, as Blemiſhes; and our Guard, as their Grievance: they would remove the Kings dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Friends, under the notion of Evil-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors; and the ſupporters of his Throne, as the infringers of their Priviledge: they would take away our diſcipline, the Fence and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of our Church, and the Penal Laws, thoſe great ſecurers of the Peace, and unity of the State; nay, ſome of them would be coming with their repeated crys of <hi>No Biſhop, No King:</hi> but we hope they ſhall never have the power of executing their extravagant Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. The Government cannot ſuffer ſuch bold attempts; and the wiſe man directs better in the words of my Text, where he charges, that <hi>the wicked ſhould be taken away.</hi> Which may have either,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A more proper and reſtrained, or</item>
               <item>2. A more large and unlimited ſignification.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt then, the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wicked may be taken in a more proper, and reſtrained ſence;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175604:11"/> and in this acception it denotes men of a reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and unquiet Spirit; of a turbulent and ſeditious humour; fretting like the foaming Sea within themſelves, and uneaſy to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; Men that know not how to bear the leaſt reſtraint that's laid upon their Pride and Ambition, but reſolve to break the moſt juſt and eaſy Yoke, and to purchaſe their own dear liberty, though ſometimes it cannot be done at any lower price, than their own Blood, and the Kingdoms ruine; Men, that go big with Faction and Diſcontent; and like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnate Waves ſwell above the higheſt Banks of Loyalty and Duty, till they break themſelves, and bring a deluge of miſeries where they come. Numbers of theſe may be ſeen, and if the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God had not prevented the malice of men, would have been deeply felt amongſt us. We may well wonder, in ſo mild a Government, what poſſibly could diſpleaſe; but Heaven it ſelf could not pleaſe the Apoſtate Angels; ſurely ſome of theſe had been trained up in Treaſon, and waited only for an opportunity of reducing their ſeditious principles into practice; ſome of them ſure had feathered their Neſts in the time of our late confuſions, and finding their ſtock of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175604:12"/> wealth and credit now in the wane, they knew no better way to buoy up their ſinking name and fortunes, than by beating up the old March, that they might ſtart a freſh Plunder. Their common note is, <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare,</hi> for as ſome of the Rebellious <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would not have the Lord to be their God, ſo theſe Engliſh Traytors would not have our moſt Gracious Soveraign to be their King; for when they found that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was deaf to their repeated Prayers for his removal, they reſolved to prove what the keen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er edge of their Sacriledgious Swords could do, and having kill'd the Heir, would have ſeized the Inheritance, and would have divided the ſpoils of Loyalty amongſt themſelves; But what form or model of Government they would have introduced in its place, we cannot ſo eaſily conjecture. Would they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured up a Common-Wealth? or have raiſed the departed Ghoſt of <hi>Democracy</hi> from the Grave where it has for ſometime laid? (and may it ever lye) kept down by the juſt reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Mankind, who have found the little Finger of that kind of Government, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion rather, heavier than the Loyns of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy ever were. However, when they had thus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175604:12"/> ſnatch'd the Scepter out of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s hands, 'twould have been more eaſy for them to pluck the Mitre from <hi>Aaron's</hi> Head. Church-diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders would have been the inſeparable compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuch State-confuſions, for State-leveling and Church-leveling are Twins, brats of the ſame monſtrous Birth; and though the former, <hi>Eſau</hi> like, be not ſo ſmooth and taking, and conſequently not ſo apt to be dandled by the Magiſtrate, who is juſtly tender of any thing that touches his prerogative; yet the latter is a more ſweet and hopeful Babe, which under the notion of Tenderneſs of Conſcience, and Chriſtian-Liberty, became the fondling of the former Age, and was ſo long cheriſhed, till it had like to have proved a <hi>Jacob,</hi> a ſupplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er indeed, and began to Exchange <hi>Jacob</hi>'s mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der voice, for <hi>Eſau's</hi> bloody, rugged Hands.</p>
            <p>Now that ſuch deplored changes were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the diſturbers of our Peace, will be more eaſy for us to believe, when we conſider, what men of the ſame leaven had but too lately acted in the time of our uncivil, and unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Wars, which I ſhall not now repeat, ſince they are ſtill ſo freſh in the bleeding memories of many thouſands amongſt us; I ſhall only
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175604:13"/> wiſh, that our Eyes may never be the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, nor our Land the Scene of ſuch another Tragedy, ſo long as Sun and Moon endureth. This ſurely is ſufficient to entitle thoſe reſtleſs and unquiet Spirits, theſe common Boutifeus and Incendiaries of our Nation, to the Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Wicked,</hi> which is given them in my Text; for though ſome of them have put on the vizard, and appearance of Zeal, and Holineſs, that under ſo charming a diſguiſe, they might draw in greater numbers of the credulous and unwary multitude; yet this does but raiſe their wickedneſs to the greateſt height, in that they dare to bring in the adored name of God to the patronage of their greateſt Crimes; and by a wretched Impoſture make bold to hang out the Flag of Heaven, when they are Marching under the Banners of Hell. Certainly there's no greater contradiction in the whole World, than Religion and Rebellion: We may as ſoon joyn the two Poles, and unite God and <hi>Belial,</hi> as find a Man who's Saint and Rebel at the ſame time. I am ſure the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> does abominate, and Damn all ſuch practiſes; nor is it poſſible for any Man, who's true to its received Principles, to turn
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175604:13"/> Traytor; ſince it gives a greater reverence, and ſecurity to the Thrones of Princes than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Doctrine under Heaven beſides: So that we are miſerably abuſed by our Friends of <hi>Rome,</hi> when they would fain lay this Brat of Treaſon at the door of our Reformation, which we may with greater Juſtice return back to themſelves, who are the more proper Dads, and Patrons of it; for that the faults and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of Princes ſhould be cenſured and puniſhed, either by their high Prieſts, or by the repreſentatives of the people, is a Doctrine that was never taught or owned by any other, than Jeſuits, or Jeſuited <hi>Fanaticks:</hi> ſome of which latter ſort are meer Machines acted on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the Will of thoſe wandring Spirits, the diſguiſed Ghoſts of our Kingdom, who walk in darkneſs, and would haunt us to a Civil Death; they find theſe zealous Brothers, fit tools to employ in the unhinging of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and in pulling of this ſtately fabrick in pieces over our ſecure Heads; when alaſs, ſhould they Midwive their Treaſon into the World without a Miſcarriage, themſelves would be firſt buried in the Ruins of it; yet are they ready to lodge any needleſs fears in their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175604:14"/> diſturbed Breaſts, and to entertain any factious whiſpers againſt their Superiours, with the ſtrongeſt apprehenſions of ſome approaching danger, which they ſtrive to prevent by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Aſſes Ears into Horns, and goring the ſides of Government, which can never be ſo peaceably eſtabliſhed, as when theſe Horns by the Sword of Juſtice are pared off, and <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away;</hi> for men of unquiet and Seditious Spirits, may be juſtly termed <hi>wicked.</hi> But</p>
            <p>Secondly, The word <hi>Wicked,</hi> may be taken in a more large and unlimited ſence, and thus it denotes the vicious, and ungodly; ſuch as are ſtrangers to morality, as well as true pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and theſe deſerve the ſevereſt cognizance of our Laws; they are moſt obnoxious to the Laws of Men, who have loſt the reſpect and obedience which is due to the Laws of God; whom neither the rewards nor terrours of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life can move nor affright; who will never take any other meaſures, but ſuch as their own luſts ſhall give; nor will make any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between things ſacred and prophane; who, if they could but avoid the cenſures of all Courts below, reſolve never to be ſcared from their Crimes with fears at ſo great a diſtance,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175604:14"/> as thoſe of the dreadful Tribunal above; and were it but as eaſy to take away the wickedneſs of theſe men, as it is to find it, how happy might we be? We have out-grown the former times in vice, and can teach new modes of pride, and luxury, to which they were the greateſt ſtrangers; ſo far have they been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done in wickedneſs by their improved poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we have changed the Simplicity of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times into Subtilty and Hypocriſy; their Loyalty into Faction and Rebellion; their Chaſtity into Chambering and Wantonneſs; their Charity into Sacriledge and Oppreſſion; their Church-Building into Church-Robbing: Theſe ſtain the Glories of our Kingdom, and find employment for the Sword of Juſtice, which ſhould purſue Sin into its cloſeſt retreats, and ſhould force it from the Horns of thoſe Altars whereunto it flies for a refuge. Nor does it always ſeek to ſhroud it ſelf in darkneſs, but goes ſometime bare-fac'd without ſhame, even in the ſight of the Sun; ſo that many who have ſo much wickedneſs as to commit the greateſt Crimes, yet have they not ſo much modeſty as to conceal them. Theſe are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Subjects of this act; and the Sword is,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175604:15"/> by the Ordinance of God, put into the, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4. Rulers hands, chiefly for this end, that he may execute wrath upon ſuch workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, who are the greateſt enemies to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms peace; ſo that whilſt we are ſenſible of no dangers, but ſuch as come either from the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> or from the <hi>Presbyterian Faction;</hi> and dread no Storm, but what's blown either from <hi>Rome,</hi> or from <hi>Geneva;</hi> we may over-look the moſt dangerous of all Plotters, and may leave the greateſt Rebels lodg'd perhaps in our own Breaſts, our Sins I mean; which once remov'd, we ſhould quickly gain a Conqueſt over all the reſt of our oppoſers; the threatning Clouds would eaſily be overblown, and and all our Foes would be made our Foot-ſtool; but ſo long as theſe are ſpared and ſuffered, it would argue the greateſt vanity and preſumption in us, to expect ſo great a Bleſſing; for wickedneſs carries always a Curſe in its Womb, of which ſooner or later it will be delivered to the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of thoſe who carry ſuch an unhappy burthen. And this brings me to</p>
            <p>The third and laſt part, to the reaſon of this removal; becauſe the ſuffering of ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men is not conſiſtent with the ſafety of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175604:15"/> Kings Perſon, nor with the due eſtabliſhment of his Throne: And if you take the word Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the former, and more reſtrained ſence, it has been abundantly confirmed by the dear experience of all Ages, that the near approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of ſuch unquiet, and ſeditious Spirits, have not only ſhaken the Thrones, but have proved fatal to the lives of the beſt of Princes; and the forbearance of ſuch, is but a turning of ſo many <hi>Tygers</hi> looſe amongſt us. Suffer ſuch Snakes to be nurſed up under the warm wing of Majeſty, and all the return which they make for their ſafety, and protection is, but to turn Parricides, and to ſting their common parent, and patron, to whoſe indulgence they owe their Lives and Fortunes; and from whom they have received that power, which they would by a monſtrous and unworthy return, employ to his Ruine: But if you take the word <hi>Wicked</hi> in the largeſt ſence for the vicious, and ungodly, it will appear very reaſonable that theſe ſhould be <hi>taken away,</hi> who are not only Traytors to God, and to themſelves, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the peace and happineſs of the Kingdom, and bring Plagues upon the places where they live; and by their Crimes are undermining
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175604:16"/> the very Throne which they pretend to guard. 'Tis true, they may make many fooliſh boaſtings of an impregnable Loyalty, and may enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all Companies with an account of what they have done and ſuffered in His Majeſties Service, when by their Vices and Debaucheries they have contributed more to the removal of his Throne, than their Swords or Councels could ever do to its eſtabliſhment. We find the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thus threatned, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 27. <hi>But if ye ſhall ſtill do wickedly, ye ſhall be conſumed both ye and your King.</hi> 'Tis not ſaid if your King do wickedly (though Princes are no more exempted from the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, than they are from the common Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Mankind) <hi>but if ye do wickedly,</hi> which ſhows, that the beſt of Princes may bear the burthen of their Subjects Sins, and may in this ſence be as our late Soveraign of Bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory was, the peoples Martyr. Is it ever like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he ſhould be a good Subject to his Prince, who's a known Rebel againſt God? or that he ſhould be ſo much concerned for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſafety of a Crown on Earth, who vouches ſuch a bold contempt of the Majeſty of Heaven? His unfaithfulneſs to himſelf in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175604:16"/> the greateſt concerns of Eternity, ſhews how unfit he is to be intruſted with his Princes ſafety; for when he ſets ſo low a price upon his own Soul, that when he is blinded by his Paſſion, or bribed by his Luſt, he'l betray it to never ending pains and torments, How can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that he ſhould ſet a greater value upon the life of his Prince? Surely, when he's blinded by his Ambition, or bribed by his Luſt, or bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotted by a Party, he'l tamely give up the moſt ſacred truſt, and may be quickly tempted to turn Rebel: (the true fear of God lays the ſtrongeſt engagement upon us to Honour the King; who will find his Throne to be the beſt guarded, when the people obey not only for wrath but for Conſcience ſake) or if he were willing to engage in ſo juſt a Quarrel as that of his Princes defence, yet will his aſſiſtance prove more inconſiderable, when his Vice has dulled his Head, and weakned his Hand, and has ſtrangely looſed the powers of his diſpirited Soul; when it has let out all that Noble Blood, which ſhould furniſh him with a ſupply of freſh Courage, ſo that he's miſerably diſabled either for his own, or for his Princes defence: His guilt makes him unable ſometime to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175604:17"/> with the terrors of his own Conſcience; then the reſolution quickly cools in his fainting Heart, and the weapons fall out of his trembling Hand, and he ſeeks a ſanctuary when he ſhould take the Field; nor can they do any great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when their Oaths are keener, and wound deeper than their Swords; and their Debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eries do a greater miſchief to themſelves, than their Blows can ever do to their Enemies; and ſurely ſuch Deboſhe's, and Carpet Knights, have ſometimes been fatal to great Men, and to the beſt Cauſe in the World, which has ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by ſo weak a defence.</p>
            <p>But futher, Sin deprives us of that which is our great, and only Bulwark againſt the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Men, and the Rage of Divels, which is, the favour and protection of Almighty God, who will never be the patron of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; this makes him our Enemy, it ſends up a bold challenge to Heaven, and bids defyance to all its Thunders; it lays us open to that vengeance from above, from which all the Powers and Policies of the whole World can never ſecure us: They may tell us of ſome clymaterical years, fatal to natural Bodies, and to Bodies Politick, beyond which, <hi>Bodin</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:175604:17"/> ſeems to affirm, that the ſtate of a Kingdom cannot ſtand; but whoever felt a Nations lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Pulſe? or could find out the critical days of a Kingdom? Are its unalterable peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods ſet down by the irreverſible Decrees of God in thoſe Sacred and Eternal Dypticks? or doth it grow weak, and old, and ſhrivelled, and bowed down with years as the Bodies of Men do? No, it may flouriſh ſtill, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue as the Days of Heaven, as the Sun and Moon before God, if his Wrath be not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by their Impieties: So that it is not any ſtrange Conjunction of the Planets, nor any Malignant Influence of the Stars, which bodes the Death of Princes, and the ruine of States; but the looſe Manners, and the ungracious Lives of the people; theſe are the ſureſt prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks of ruine; and if theſe be but once taken away, all is ſafe. This the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens did conclude; for when one was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, what was the ſtrongeſt Guard to a Kings Throne? He anſwered, <hi>The Piety and Innocence of his Subjects: For if they were vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, an Hundred Brazen Walls would prove too weak for its defence.</hi> Nay, <hi>Matchiavel</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf owns the wickedneſs of Men, to be the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175604:18"/> ruine of Kingdoms. But we need no ſuch Teſtimonies, finding this Truth confirmed by the Sacred Book of God, and by the common experience of Mankind. We may Read it in the Ruins of many once flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; and may find, that God hath turned many fruitful Land into Barrenneſs, for the wickedneſs of thoſe that dwelt therein: So evident is it, that if Atheiſme, and Debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery, Faction and Hereſy be ſo common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, theſe Sins, like the Traytors in the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe, will do us more miſchief than Thouſands of other enemies in many years could ever do. The reaſonableneſs of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution does, I hope, now appear unto you, and you ſee that men of Seditious ſpirits, and ungodly lives are juſtly obnoxious to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of our Laws; they are to be <hi>taken away,</hi> becauſe the forbearance of ſuch is inconſiſtent with the due ſettlement of the Kings Throne, and the Kingdoms Peace; and when this is once done, we may expect the Bleſſing ſet down in the latter part of my Text, where we find a confluence of all thoſe Bleſſings that can make an happy Prince, and a thriving people: Here Mercy and Truth are met together;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175604:18"/> Righteouſneſs and Peace have kiſſed each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and whatſoever can add to the glory and ſecurity of a Nation, we find it here ſumm'd up in one ſhort period. For there do the people ſit under the kindeſt influences of Heaven; there do they enjoy the greateſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours upon Earth, where the Kings Throne is eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſs; a Bleſſing of ſuch an abſolute neceſſity to the common Peace and ſafety of Mankind, that the want of this does not only take away the flouriſhing, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being of a Kingdom; Take but Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment once out of the World, and we ſhall quickly find it run back into a State infinitely more deplored than that of its firſt confuſion; the whole Earth would be nothing elſe, but a vaſt Wilderneſs; but an howling deſert of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and Savages; but a Type of Hell; and men would be but a more cunning kind of brutes or fiends rather, devouring, and being devoured one of another; and Government it ſelf without Monarchy, without the Throne of a King, would be a monſtrous, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Body with many Heads, whoſe diſorders, would be its death; it would quickly crumble it ſelf in pieces by its private Factions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175604:19"/> it would be ſubdivided into ſeveral Parties and Cabals, each whereof would ſtrive to bear down their oppoſers, and to raiſe themſelves upon the ruins of thoſe whom they either fear or hate; and when they have gain'd a ſhare in the Government, they would ſooner be drawn to emprove their ſhort liv'd power for their private advantage, and might be tempted to take meaſures from their own coveteouſneſs and ambition, rather than from the Publick Good: So that no other kind of Government can make ſo reaſonable a proviſion for the Peace and happineſs of a people, as Monarchy can do: And Monarchy it ſelf, the Throne of a King, without a due eſtabliſhment, will prove but a tottering, and uneaſy Seat, like old <hi>Ely's</hi> ſtool, from whence ſome of the moſt deſerving Princes (worthy of a better fate) have been thrown headlong down the precipice of an untimely death; and even the firmeſt ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſettlement of a Throne without Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, would be nothing elſe but a medley of Tyranny and Injuſtice. Now here all theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences are avoided, and we meet with a concurrence of all the requiſites to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms Peace and hapineſs. For here is,</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:175604:19"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> The beſt Government's the Throne of a King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Here is the beſt Guard, the ſtrongeſt ſupporter of his Throne, and that is good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and due eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Here is the beſt means in the whole world to procure, and continue ſo deſirable a ſettlement; and that is Righteouſneſs. I have no time to enlarge upon each of theſe particulars, I ſhall wiſh that theſe may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be matters of Speculation and Diſcourſe, but of Experience and Enjoyment. We have at preſent all theſe Bleſſings, which are the Glory of our Land, the grief and envy of our Enemies; we have the beſt of Governments, under the beſt of Princes; the beſt Laws, and the beſt Religion under Heaven: May theſe be continued to us, and to our poſterity, till Time it ſelf be outdated, and loſt in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; by that Favour of that God, by whom Kings Reign, and Princes Decree Juſtice: To whom be all Honour, Praiſe, and Glory now and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:175604:20"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed and Sold by <hi>Iſaac Cleave.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſecond part of the <hi>Inſtitutes of the Laws of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Containing an expoſition of <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third part of the <hi>Inſtitutes of the Laws of England,</hi> Concerning High-Treaſon, and other Pleas of the Crown and Criminal Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The fourth part of the <hi>Inſtitutes of the Laws of England,</hi> Concerning the Jurisdiction of Courts, all three by <hi>Ed. Cook, Mil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reports</hi> of that Reverand and Learned Judge, the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Henry Hobert</hi> Knight and Barro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net; Lord Chief Juſtice of His Majeſties Court of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Offinia Brevium,</hi> Select and approved forms of <hi>Judicial Writs,</hi> and other <hi>Proceſs,</hi> with their <hi>Returns</hi> and <hi>Entries</hi> in the Court of <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> as alſo Special Pleadings to Writs of <hi>Scire facias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Vindication of the true Chriſtian Religion, in oppoſition to the Abomination of Popery,</hi> in a Sermon upon <hi>Exekiel</hi> 21. 24, 25, 26, 27. Being the Text appointed for Maſter <hi>Whitebread,</hi> one of the Popiſh Conſprators, to Preach upon the accompliſhing their wicked deſign. By <hi>J. Thomas,</hi> Rect. of <hi>St. Nicholas,</hi> Preached at <hi>Cardiff.</hi> before the Bayliffs and Aldermen there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Popes Cabinet unlocked, or a Catalogue of all the Popes Indulgences belonging to the Order of</hi> St. <hi>Mary;</hi> together with a Liſt of all the Indulgences dayly, yearly, and for ever, Written in <hi>Italian,</hi> by <hi>Fr. Arcangelo Tortello,</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:175604:20"/> the Order of St. <hi>Mary;</hi> and now tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>John Sidway,</hi> late Seminary Prieſt; but now of the Reformed Religion, and Vicar of <hi>Selling</hi> in <hi>Kent;</hi> and one of the Diſcoverers of the Horrid Popiſh Plot, with the Cauſe of his Converſion. Whereunto is added an <hi>Appendix,</hi> by the Tranſlator, in which the grounds and foundations of the ſaid Indulgences being examined, are utterly overthrown; and by conſequence, Indulgences themſelves apparently proved to be mear Cheats: And alſo ſhewing, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth lay the chief <hi>Baſis</hi> of their Religion on Indulgences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Book of Rates</hi> now uſed in the <hi>Sum Cuſtom-Houſe</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> Containing the Bulls, Diſpenſations and Pardons for all manner of villanies and wickedneſs, with the ſeveral ſums of Money given, and to be paid for them. The ſecond Impreſſion.</p>
            <p>To which is added the <hi>New Creed</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſeveral other Remarkable things not in the former Edition.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Anthony Egane, B. D.</hi> late Confeſſor General of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> but now of the Reformed Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands Improvement Reviv'd,</hi> in a Treatiſe of all manner of Husbandry and Trade, by Land and Sea, plainly diſcovering the ſeveral ways of improving all ſorts of waſte and barren Grounds, and enriching all Earths with the natural quality of all Lands, and the ſeveral Seeds and Plants which muſt naturally thrive therein; together with the manner of Planting all ſorts of Trees and Underwoods, with two ſeveral Chains to plant Seeds or Sets by, with ſeveral directions for planting of Hops; alſo the way of ordering Cattel, with ſeveral ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations about Sheep, and choice of Cows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Smith,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:175604:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
